Guide to the New York Taxi Workers Alliance Records WAG.319
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
New York Taxi Workers Alliance Records
Bulk, 1997-2010
1972-2011
WAG.319
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
13.0 linear feet in 12 record cartons, 1 manuscript box and 1 oversized flat box
The New York Taxi Workers’ Alliance was founded in 1998 by members of the Lease Drivers Coalition (LDC), an advocacy project of the Committee Against Anti-Asian Violence (CAAAV). The union, led by Executive Director Bhairavi Desai since its inception, fights for structural change in the taxi driving industry, regularly ranked by the Department of Labor as one of the most dangerous job in the country. The NYTWA supports drivers through legal advocacy, health benefits, and numerous campaigns fighting for safety and economic justice for taxi workers. Because taxi drivers are considered independent contractors, they cannot engage in collective bargaining. Despite this impediment, the NYTWA claims it has increased taxi drivers’ incomes by 35%-45%, including implementation of the first-ever Living Wage standard for US taxi drivers in 2004. The records of the New York Taxi Workers’ Alliance document the organization from its growth out of the Lease Driver Coalition (an initiative of the Committee Against Anti-Asian Violence) in 1998 to its 2012 status as a national union and a member of the AFL-CIO in 2010. The records illusrtate the growth of the union in membership, funding, and media coverage, and the specific challenges of 21st century labor organizing in a transient and ethnically diverse population. The collection primarily documents the two major activities of the union: campaigns and legal services.
New York Taxi Workers Alliance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Records of the New York Taxi Workers Alliance (NYTWA) were donated to the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive by the NYTWA in February, 2011. The accession number associated with this gift is 2011.037. Another small donation of recent NYTWA publications was made in 2013.
Access Restrictions
All materials in the collection are open for researcher use without restriction. Some material in Series II: Legal, relating to legal advocacy cases in support of individual members, have been redacted to ensure the privacy of these individuals. Names, addresses, phone numbers, hack numbers, and other information which might identify individuals have been blacked out.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into three series:
Series I: Campaigns, 1994-2010
Series II: Legal, 1998-2010
Series III: Administrative, 1974-2011
New York Taxi Workers Alliance (NYTWA) History
The New York Taxi Workers’ Alliance was founded in 1998 by members of the Lease Drivers Coalition (LDC), an advocacy project of the Committee Against Anti-Asian Violence (CAAAV). The union, led by Executive Director Bhairavi Desai since its inception, fights for structural change in the taxi driving industry, regularly ranked by the Department of Labor as one of the most dangerous job in the country. The NYTWA supports drivers through legal advocacy, health education, and numerous campaigns fighting for safety and economic justice for taxi workers. Because taxi drivers are considered independent contractors, the union cannot engage in collective bargaining.
Despite this limitation, the NYTWA uses legislation, work-stoppage strikes, demonstrations, and petitions to affect change. They mobilize drivers and build membership through meetings, outreach and fairs in airport waiting lots, industry research, organizational partnerships, and assisting drivers with tickets and fines. The NYTWA claims it has increased taxi drivers’ incomes by 35%-45%, including advocating for the implementation of the first-ever Living Wage standard for US taxi drivers in 2004.
In May 1998, four months after their formation, the NYTWA organized a 24-hour strike of thousands of licensed taxi drivers in protest of proposed Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC) regulations that would quadruple liability-insurance costs, increase fines and probationary periods for new drivers, and increase the frequency of drug and alcohol testing for drivers. The NYTWA demanded a moratorium on the new rules, an in-depth study of the taxi industry, and an end to double ticketing (the practice of issuing multiple tickets at the same time for similar driving infractions). Though the strike did not affect immediate change on TLC regulations, it was influential because it solidified the NYTWA as a union and was able to bring together workers from a notoriously segmented group with no central point of organization.
Early organizing activity for the union includes City Council Bill 472, which fought against TLC codes of conduct for drivers (primarily regarding license revoking procedures) which the council ruled to be “onerous” on drivers. Another early campaign fought against the long wait times drivers faced at the Queen Boulevard TLC Office, which took valuable time out of a drivers’ average 60-hour work week. The NYTWA focused their efforts in the early 2000s on studying the impact of September 11, 2001 on taxi drivers and New York City immigrants and subsequent relief efforts (including federal disaster assistance for taxi drivers).
During the mid-2000s, the union focused on the detrimental effects new taxi technology (malfunctioning credit card machines, the loss of 5% on fares from credit card use, and GPS tracking) had on driver earnings and individual rights. They also worked to raise the wages of drivers through economic justice campaigns, which fought for fare increases, caps on the cost of leasing cars and medallions, and for a fuel surcharge on all fares. Union activity in the late 2000s concentrated on health initiatives; Intro 705, a bill which allowed drivers to choose credit card machine operators; and the Taxi Driver Protection Act, which called for heavier penalties for assaults on drivers and a sticker in each taxi warning of these penalties.
The NYTWA also spends much of its resources on providing discounted or pro bono legal, financial management, and health services for its members. The NYTWA claims a membership of 16,000 drivers and was voted into the New York City Central Labor Council in 2007 as the first non-collective bargaining agent member of a Central Labor Council in the US. Together with the Taxi Workers Alliance of Pennsylvania, the union hosted a conference of international taxi unions in 2007, which resulted in the creation of the National Taxi Workers Alliance, now headquartered at the NYTWA.
History of Taxicabs in New York City
Despite the iconic status of yellow cabs in the city of New York, documentation of the industry and its workers is sparse. The transitory nature of the industry and its history of union creation, corruption, and short-lived organizing efforts made it both hard to organize, and hard to document. Henry Allen started the first taxi fleet in New York City in 1907 (The New York Taxicab Company), with the first organizing and strike efforts taking place just one year later over the cost of uniform rentals and gas prices.
By the Great Depression there were more cabs on the streets of New York than there are in 2013 (about 16,000 in 1932 compared to 13,000 in 2013). To regulate this number, the city passed the Haas Act and introduced the medallion system. A medallion licenses a car to pick up and taxi passengers in New York City. By restricting the number of medallions, rather than driver licenses, the city can regulate the number of taxicabs on the streets of New York. More than half of the medallions created went to fleet owners who rent cars and medallions to licensed drivers for two shifts a day. The rest of the medallions were reserved for driver-owners, who are required to drive for a certain number of shifts before they can lease the medallion. The Act allowed for the transfer of medallions between owners and since the number of medallions did not increase until 1996, the cost increased exponentially. The cost was around $10 in 1937. By 2012, medallions sold for almost $1 million.
In 1971, the city created the Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC) to regulate the taxi and limousine industry, which had previously been under the jurisdiction of the New York City police department. The TLC is in charge of licensing and regulating the taxi industry while the NYPD enforces traffic laws. Thus, New York City taxi drivers must be aware of the rules and regulations of several agencies: The Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC), the New York City Police Department (NYPD), and the Department of Motor Vehicles (DMV).
In 1979, the city legalized the leasing system. This system chaged drivers’ status from employee to independent contractor. Instead of receiving a percentage of the days’ earnings, drivers now pay a set amount to lease the car and medallion for the day or week. Over the next few years, all garages moved to the leasing system. Since then, taxi drivers lease cars (and their medallions) from fleet garages or brokers by the day or by the week. A “DOV” driver (Driver Owned Vehicle) owns their vehicle but rents the medallion from the broker. By 2011, there were over 13,000 medallions and almost 50,000 licensed cab drivers. Since the retirement of the iconic "checker cab" in New York, most taxicabs were Ford Crown Victorias, one of the cheapest options of the TLC-approved cars until the 2010s. Because the Crown Victoria was discontinued in 2011, the TLC and Mayor Bloomberg introduced the Taxi of Tomorrow plan, which plans to replace all existing cars with an approved Nissan design from 2013-2018. The plan was controversial because the approved Nissan was neither an hybrid, nor was it wheel-chair accessible.
The taxi industry has always employed the recent immigrant population in New York City, though the proportion of drivers born outside of the U.S. increased dramatically in the last quarter of the 20th century. By 2005, less than 10% of drivers were born inside of the U.S. and the majority came from the South Asian countries of Bangladesh, India, and Pakistan. This demographic composition has a wide-ranging impact on the industry and its patterns of organizing.
Related Archival Materials
Taxi Rank and File Coalition Oral History Collection OH 013
New York City Taxi Drivers’ Union Oral History Collection OH 028
United Taxi Workers Organizing Committee Records WAG 005
Taxi Rank and File Coalition Records WAG 139
Scope and Content Note
The records of the New York Taxi Workers’ Alliance document the organization from its growth out of the Lease Driver Coalition (an initiative of the Committee Against Anti-Asian Violence) in 1998 to its 2012 status as a national union and a member of the AFL-CIO in 2010. The records illusrtate the growth of the union in membership, funding, and media coverage, and the specific challenges of 21st century labor organizing in a transient and ethnically diverse population. The collection primarily documents the two major activities of the union: campaigns and legal services.
Without collective bargaining, campaigns are the major way the NYTWA affects change in the industry. Since its founding in 1998, the NYTWA has initiated numerous campaigns working toward increasing the wage of drivers, advocating for driver health and safety, fighting against TLC rules and regulations, and increasing public awareness of industry issues. The NYTWA provides discounted or pro-bono legal assistance to aid drivers in understanding and navigating the constantly changing traffic regulations and complicated TLC court system, in addition to the multiple city agencies they contend with on a daily basis, The Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC), the New York City Police Department (NYPD), and the Department of Motor Vehicles (DMV).
Materials that document these campaigns include New York City Council outreach, flyers and distribution materials for drivers and the general public, proposed bills and legislation, internal workplans, industry research and clippings, and driver surveys. The records document their interactions with the media, drivers, the NYTWA Organizing Committee, and partnerships with related organizations.
Through these records, researchers can find information about evolving transportation technologies, the impact of September 11, 2001 on South Asian workers and the transportation industry, taxi drivers in the media, the rising cost of medallions, the effects of the legal system on the immigrant population of New York, changing traffic laws and restrictions, industry-specific health concerns, and efforts to educate the public about the industry.
Also represented in this collection are the many organizations that operate within the taxi industry. The NYTWA is the only group that advocates for and consists of taxi drivers themselves. There are several realted organizations that fight for taxi garages and medallion owners, including The Metropolitan Taxi Cab Board of Trade (MTBOT), Committee for Taxi Safety, and Greater New York Taxi Association. Over time, the NYTWA's working relationships with related organizations evolved. In particular, the NYTWA works more closely with the Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC) under the leadership of Commissioner Yassky (2010-2017), in comparison with Commissioner Daus (2001-2010). The NYTWA also initiated partnerships with other organizations to aid in campaign work and research projects, including the Brennan Center for Justice, the National Immigration Law Center, and the Urban Justice Center.
Due to the small size of the NYTWA office staff and its use of email and phone communication, the collection contains little documentation of internal office interactions. This is also apparent in the lack of internal structure visible in the records themselves. Operating with only a few full time employees, the small staff performed all tasks in the organization – answering phones, doing research and outreach, writing articles, and attending meetings. Evidence of the fast paced office and makeshift orgnaizational strategies can be seen in the way that documents were used and reused. Most pieces of paper have been used for multiple purposes and passed through many hands – an unused flyer about one campaign became paper for taking notes about another. The documents reflect the nature of working in a reactive environment with less time for planning and internal organization. Instead, staff and volunteers for the NYTWA focused on how to affect the most change in a rapidly evolving industry.
Appraisal Note
Personnel materials and membership lists with identifying information have been removed from the collection and returned to the NYTWA. Book titles already housed in the Tamiment Library collection were also returned.
Bibliography
Fine, Janice. Worker Centers: Organizing Communities at the Edge of the Dream. Ithaca, NY: ILR Press, 2006.
Hodges, Graham Russell. Taxi!: A Social History of the New York City Cabdriver. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2007.
Mathew, Biju. Taxi!: Cabs and Capitalism in New York City. Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2008.
Schaller Consulting. The New York City Taxicab Fact Book. Brooklyn, NY: Schaller Consulting, 2006.
New York (N.Y.). Taxi and Limousine Commission.; New York Taxi Workers Alliance.; Asian Americans |x Economic conditions.; Asian Americans |x Employment.; Asian Americans |x Legal status, laws, etc.; Asian Americans |x Social conditions.; Asian Americans |z New York (State) |z New York.; Emigration and immigration law |z United States.; Global Positioning System.; Immigrants |z United States |x Civil rights.; Legal aid |z New York (State) |z New York.; Legal documents.; Legal services |z New York (State) |z New York.; New York (N.Y.); Publications.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; Strikes and lockouts |x Transport workers |z New York (State) |z New York |x History.; Taxicab drivers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Taxicab drivers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Taxicabs |x Fares; Taxicabs |x Law and legislation; Taxicabs.; Transport workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State); Transport workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York |x History.; Transport workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Transport workers |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: Campaigns, 1994-2010
  Arrangement
  This series is organized by campaign and arranged chronologically by campaign start date. Photographs (originally in binders or developing envelopes) were kept in their original order and were placed at the end of this series.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series documents the public facing activities of the union and its efforts to raise awareness about and change laws regarding driver working conditions. The series begins with organizing efforts of the Lease Driver Committee and the 1998 strikes that solidified the NYTWA as an organizing body. Materials that document these campaigns include New York City Council outreach, flyers and distribution materials for drivers and the general public, bills and legislation, internal workplans, industry research and clippings, and driver surveys.
  Without collective bargaining, these campaigns show the many ways that the NYTWA advocated for change in the industry. The NYTWA focus their legislative and advocacy campaigns on immigrant rights, a living wage for drivers, the exploitative practices of fleet garages and brokers, and health and safety. Major campaigns include (in chronological order) City Council Bill 472, 9/11 impact studies and aid efforts, Fuel Surcharge, Economic Justice, Stop GPS, and the Taxi Driver Protection Act.
  Economic Justice is a term the NYTWA used to describe campaigns in the mid-2000s that relate to raising the wage of taxi drivers through fare raises and lowering the cost of daily or weekly cab leasing. Campaigns relating to 9/11 use member surveys to document the effects of the event on driver income and treatment. These surveys and other research was used to advocate for Federal Emeregency Management Agency (FEMA) funds as well as housing rent assistance from the Bridge Fund. Stop GPS is the most well represented campaign in this series and spans 2004-2008. Stop GPS fought against malfunctioning credit card machines, the loss of 5% on fares from credit card use, and GPS tracking.
  Health campaigns are interspersed throughout this series as new initiatives took place at different times throughout the union’s tenure. Other minor campaigns advocate for drivers that have been injured or killed while driving, Ford Crown Victoria safety, the Queens Boulevard TLC Office Campaign, peace rallies, efforts to democratize TLC courts, immigrant rights, and taxi cab accessibility. Photographs at the end of this series document most of these campaigns.
  - Lease Driver Coalition, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lease Driver Coalition: Workplans (I), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lease Driver Coalition: Workplans (II), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lease Driver Coalition: Demonstration, Aug 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lease Driver Coalition: Flyers: Related Organizations, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lease Driver Coalition: South Asia, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lease Driver Coalition and New York Taxi Workers Alliance, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1998 Strikes: Demands, May 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1998 Strikes: Flyers, May 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1998 Strikes: Community Outreach, May 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1998 Strikes: Public Opinion Flyers, May 1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1998 Strikes: Public Support Letters, May 1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1998 Strikes: Clippings, May 1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1998 Strikes: Community Support, May-Jun 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1998 Strikes: Clippings (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1998 Strikes: Flyers (Box 1, Folder 18, Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1998 Strikes: Press Releases (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1998 Strikes: Taxi Industry Flyers (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1998 Strikes: Flyer and Translations (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1998 Strikes: Public Flyers (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1998 Strikes: Organizing and Documentation (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1998 Strikes: New York City Taxi Owners Association (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1998 Strikes: Information Packets, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1998 Strikes: Distribution Materials, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - City Council Campaign: Introduction Flyer, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - General, circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - City Council Bill 472: Industry Research, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - City Council Bill 472: City Council Outreach, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - City Council Bill 472: City Council Proposals, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - City Council Bill 472: Distribution Materials, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - City Council Bill 472: Industry Statements, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - City Council Bill 472: New York Taxi Workers' Alliance (NYTWA) Proposals, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - City Council Bill 472: Legal Correspondence, Nov 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - City Council Bill 472: Petitions, circa 1999 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - City Council Bill 472: Introduction B, Apr 1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - City Council Bill 472: Introduction C, Apr 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Queens Boulevard Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC) Office Campaign, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Queens Boulevard Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC) Office Campaign, Jun 1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lease Cap: Pending Work, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 9/11 Impact: Disaster Unemployment Assistance, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 9/11 Impact: Labor and Community Response, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 9/11 Impact: Asian Americans and Immigrants, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 9/11 Impact: Research, circa 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 9/11 Impact: Driver Survey, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 9/11 Impact: Driver Survey (I), circa 2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 9/11 Impact: Driver Survey (II), circa 2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 9/11 Impact: Bridge Fund Applications, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 9/11 Impact: Taxi Drivers in New York City Study, circa 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 9/11 Impact: Bridge Fund, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 9/11 Impact: Moving Forward Funding, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ford Accountability Campaign, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ford Crown Victoria Safety, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Justice for Yousef, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Peace Rally for South Asia, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Health Fair: Financial, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Fare and Lease, circa 2002 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Fare and Lease, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Fare and Lease: Lease Information, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Economic Justice: Pilot Survey, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Economic Justice: Letters to Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC), Feb 2002 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Economic Justice: Press, Mar -May 2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Economic Justice, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Economic Justice: Workplans, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Economic Justice: Driver Mobilization, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Economic Justice: Liu, John, Apr 2003 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Economic Justice: Public Hearing, Apr 2003 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Economic Justice: Petition to Initiate Rulemaking, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Economic Justice: Lower Wages/Higher Fares, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Economic Justice: Fare and Lease Research, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Economic Justice: Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC) Petitions, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Economic Justice: Reply to Taxi and Limousine Commission (TLC) Letter, Sep 2003 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Economic Justice: Support, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 39)